<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Kyle M. Douglass (Posts about optics)</title><link>https://kylemdouglass.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://kylemdouglass.com/categories/cat_optics.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2024 &lt;a href="mailto:kyle.m.douglass@gmail.com"&gt;Kyle M. Douglass&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Creative Commons License BY-NC-SA"
style="border-width:0; margin-bottom:12px;"
src="https://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-sa/4.0/88x31.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Nov 2024 14:47:38 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Coordinate Systems for Modeling Microscope Objectives</title><link>https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/coordinate-systems-for-modeling-microscope-objectives/</link><dc:creator>Kyle M. Douglass</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;A common model for infinity corrected microscope objectives is that of an aplanatic and telecentric optical system. In many developments of this model, emphasis is placed upon the calculation of the electric field near the focus. However, this has the effect that the definition of the coordinate systems and geometry are conflated with the determination of the fields. In addition, making the model amenable to computation often occurs as an afterthought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post I will explore the geometry of an aplanatic system for modeling high NA objectives with an emphasis on computational implementations. My approach follows Novotny and Hecht&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/coordinate-systems-for-modeling-microscope-objectives/#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and Herrera and Quinto-Su&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/coordinate-systems-for-modeling-microscope-objectives/#fn:2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Model Components&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The model system is illustrated below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src="https://kylemdouglass.com/images/aplanatic-telecentric-system.png"&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A high NA, infinity corrected microscope objective as an aplanatic and telecentric optical system.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this model, we abstract over the details of the objective by representing it as four surfaces:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A back focal plane containing an aperture stop&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A back principal plane, \( P \)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A front principal surface, \( P' \)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A front focal plane&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The space to the left of the back principal plane is called the infinity space. The space to the right of the front principal surface is called the sample space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We let the infinity space refractive index \( n_1 = 1 \) because it is in air. The refractive index \( n_2 \) is the refractive index of the immersion medium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The unit vectors \( \mathbf{n} \) are not used in this discussion; they are relevant for computing the fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Assumptions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We make one assumption: the system obeys the sine condition. The meaning of this will be explained later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An aplanatic system is one that obeys the sine condition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will not assume the intensity law to conserve energy because it is only necessary when computing the electric field near the focus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Aperture Stop and Back Focal Plane&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aperture stop (AS) of an optical system is the element that limits the angle of the marginal ray.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The system is telecentric because the aperture stop is located in the back focal plane (BFP). We can shape the focal field by spatially modulating any of the amplitude, phase, or polarization of the incident light in a plane conjugate to the BFP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Back Principal Plane&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the plane in infinity space at which rays appear to refract. It is a plane because rays coming from a point in the front focal plane all emerge into the infinity space in the same direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strictly speaking, focus field calculations require us to propagate the field from the AS to the back principal plane before computing the Debye diffraction integral, but this step is often omitted&lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/coordinate-systems-for-modeling-microscope-objectives/#fn:3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The assumptions of paraxial optics should hold here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Front Principal Surface&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The front principal surface is the surface at which rays appear to refract in the sample space. It is a surface because&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;this is a non-paraxial system, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;we assumed the sine condition.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sine condition states that refraction of a ray coming from an on-axis point in the front focal plane occurs on a spherical cap centered upon the focal point. The distance from the optical axis of the point of intersection of the ray with the surface is proportional to the sine of the angle that the ray makes with the axis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The principal surface is in the far field of the electric field coming from the focal region. For this reason, we can represent a point on this surface as representing a single ray or a plane wave&lt;sup id="fnref2:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/coordinate-systems-for-modeling-microscope-objectives/#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Front Focal Plane&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This plane is located a distance \( n_2 f \) from the principal surface&lt;sup id="fnref:4"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/coordinate-systems-for-modeling-microscope-objectives/#fn:4"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. It is not at a distance \( f \) from this surface. This is a result of imaging in an immersion medium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Geometry and Coordinate Systems&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Aperture Stop Radius&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aperture stop radius \( R \) corresponds to the distance from the axis to the point where the marginal ray intersects the front prinicpal surface. In the sample space, the marginal ray travels at an angle \( \theta_{max} \) with respect to the axis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under the sine condition, this height is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ R = n_2 f \sin{ \theta_{max} } = f \, \text{NA} $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The right-most expression uses the definition of the numerical aperture \( \text{NA} \equiv n \sin{ \theta_{max} } \).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compare this result to the oft-cited expression for the entrance pupil diameter of an objective lens: \( D = 2 f \, \text{NA} \). They are the same. This makes sense because an entrance pupil is either&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;an image of an aperture stop, or&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a physical stop.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Back Principal Plane&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two independent coordinate systems in the back principal plane:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the spatial coordinate system defining the far field positions \( \left( x_{\infty} , y_{\infty} \right) \), and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the coordinate system of the angular spectrum of plane waves \( \left( k_x, k_y \right) \).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The Far Field Coordinate System&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The far field coordinate system may be written in Cartesian form as \( \left( x_{\infty} , y_{\infty} \right) \). It also has a cylindrical representation as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$\begin{eqnarray}
\rho &amp;amp;=&amp;amp; \sqrt{x_{\infty}^2 + y_{\infty}^2} \\
\phi &amp;amp;=&amp;amp; \arctan \left( \frac{y_{\infty}}{x_{\infty}} \right)
\end{eqnarray}$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cylindrical representation appears to be preferred in textbook developments of the model. The Cartesian representation is likely preferred for computational models because it works naturally with two-dimensional arrays of numbers, and because beam shaping elements such as spatial light modulators are rectangular arrays of pixels&lt;sup id="fnref2:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/coordinate-systems-for-modeling-microscope-objectives/#fn:2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The Angular Spectrum Coordinate System&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each point in the angular spectrum coordinate system represents a plane wave in the sample space that is traveling at an angle \( \theta \) to the axis according to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$\begin{eqnarray}
k_x &amp;amp;=&amp;amp; k \sin \theta \cos \phi \\
k_y &amp;amp;=&amp;amp; k \sin \theta \sin \phi \\
k_z &amp;amp;=&amp;amp; k \cos \theta
\end{eqnarray}$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where \( k = 2 \pi n_2 / \lambda = n_2 k_0 \).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along the y-axis ( \( x_{\infty} = 0 \) ), the maximum value of \( k_y \) is \(n_2 k_0 \sin \theta_{max} = k_0 \, \text{NA} \).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Substitute in the expression \( \text{NA} = R / f \) and we get \(k_{y, max} = k_0 R / f\). But \( R = y_{\infty, max} \). This (and similar reasoning for the x-axis) implies that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$\begin{eqnarray}
k_x &amp;amp;=&amp;amp; k_0 x_{\infty} / f \\
k_y &amp;amp;=&amp;amp; k_0 y_{\infty} / f
\end{eqnarray}$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above equations link the angular spectrum coordinate system to the far field coordinate system. They are no longer independent once \( f \) and \( \lambda \) are specified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Numerical Meshes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are four free parameters for defining the coordinate systems of the numerical meshes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The numerical aperture, \( \text{NA} \)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The wavelength, \( \lambda \)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The focal length, \( f \)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The linear mesh size, \( L \)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is a figure that illustrates the construction of the meshes. Both the far field and angular spectrum coordinate systems are represented by a \( L \times L \) array. \( L = 16 \) in the figure below. In general the value of \( L \) should be a power of 2 to help ensure the efficiency of the Fast Fourier Transform (FFT). By considering only powers of 2, we need only consider arrays of even size as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src="https://kylemdouglass.com/images/pupil-function-simulation-mesh.png"&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A numeric mesh representing the far field and angular spectrum coordinate systems of a microscope objective. Fields are sampled at the center of each mesh pixel.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fields are defined on a region of circular support that is centered on this array. The radius of the domain of the far field coordinate system is \( f \text{NA} \); the radius of the domain of the angular spectrum coordinate system is \( k_0 \text{NA} \).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The boxes that are bound by the gray lines indicate the location of each field sample. The \( \left( x_{\infty} , y_{\infty} \right) \) and the \( \left( k_x, k_y \right) \) coordinate systems are sampled at the center of each gray box. The origin is therefore not sampled, which will help avoid division by zero errors when the fields are eventually computed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The figure suggests that we could create only one mesh and scale it by either \( f \text{NA} \) or \( k_0 \text{NA} \) depending on which coordinate system we are working with. The normalized coordinates become \( \left( x_{\infty} / \left( f \text{NA} \right), y_{\infty} / \left( f \text{NA} \right) \right) \) and \( \left( k_x / \left( k_0 \text{NA} \right), k_y / \left( k_0 \text{NA} \right) \right) \).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1D Mesh Example&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an example, let \( L = 16 \). To four decimal places, the normalized coordinates are \( -1.0000, -0.8667, \ldots, -0.0667, 0.0667, \ldots, 0.8667, 1.0000 \).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spacing between array elements is \( 2 / \left( L - 1 \right) = 0.1333 \). Note that 0 is not included in the 1D mesh as it goes from -0.0667 to 0.0667.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A 2D mesh is easily constructed from the 1D mesh using tools such as NumPy's &lt;a href="https://numpy.org/doc/stable/reference/generated/numpy.meshgrid.html"&gt;meshgrid&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Back Principal Plane Mesh Spacings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the x-direction, the mesh spacing of the far field coordinate system is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \Delta x_{\infty} = 2 R / \left( L - 1 \right) = 2 f \text{NA} / \left( L - 1 \right) $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the \( k_x \)-direction, the mesh spacing of the angular spectrum coordinate system is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \Delta k_x = 2 k_{max} / \left( L - 1 \right) = 2 k_0 \text{NA} / \left( L - 1 \right) $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note the symmetry between these two expressions. One scales with \( f \text{NA} \) and the other \( k_0 \text{NA} \). Recall that these are free parameters of the model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Sample Space Mesh Spacing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is interesting to compute the spacing between mesh elements \( \Delta x \) in the sample space when the fields are eventually computed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sampling angular frequency in the sample space is \( k_S = 2 \pi / \Delta x \).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Nyquist-Shannon sampling theory states that the maximum informative angular frequency is \( k_{max} = k_S / 2 \).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the previous section, we know that \( k_{max} = \left(L - 1 \right) \Delta k_x / 2 \), and that \( \Delta k_x = 2 k_0 \text{NA} / \left( L - 1 \right) \).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Combining all the previous expressions and simplifying, we get:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$\begin{eqnarray}
k_S &amp;amp;=&amp;amp; 2 k_{max} \\
2 \pi / \Delta x &amp;amp;=&amp;amp; \left(L - 1 \right) \Delta k_x \\
2 \pi / \Delta x &amp;amp;=&amp;amp; \left(L - 1 \right) \left[ 2 k_0 \text{NA} / \left( L - 1 \right) \right] \\
2 \pi / \Delta x &amp;amp;=&amp;amp; \left(L - 1 \right) \left[ 2 \left(2 \pi / \lambda \right) \text{NA} / \left( L - 1 \right) \right]
\end{eqnarray}$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solving the above expression for \( \Delta x \), we arrive at&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \Delta x = \frac{\lambda}{2 \text{NA}} $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;which is of course the Abbe diffraction limit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Effect of not Sampling the Origin&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Herrera and Quinto-Su&lt;sup id="fnref3:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/coordinate-systems-for-modeling-microscope-objectives/#fn:2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; point out that an error will be introduced if we naively apply the FFT to compute the field components in the \( \left( k_x, k_y \right) \) coordinate system because the origin is not sampled, whereas the FFT assumes that we sample the zero frequency component. The effect is that the result of the FFT has a constant phase error that accounts for a half-pixel shift in each direction of the mesh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider again the 1D mesh example with \(L = 16 \): \( -1.0000, -0.8667, \ldots, -0.0667, 0.0667, \ldots, 0.8667, 1.0000 \)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Python and other languages that index arrays starting at 0, the origin is located at \(L / 2 - 0.5 \), i.e. halfway between the samples at index 7 and 8. A lateral shift in Fourier space is equivalent to a phase shift in real space:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \phi_{shift} \left(X, Y \right) =  -j 2 \pi \frac{0.5}{L} X - j 2 \pi \frac{0.5}{L} Y $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where \( X \) and \( Y \) are normalized coordinates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, I am uncertain whether the phasor with the above argument needs to be multiplied or divided with the result of the FFT because 1. there are a few typos in the signs for the coordinate system bounds in the manuscript of Herrera and Quinto-Su, and 2. the correction was developed for use in MATLAB, which indexes arrays starting at 1. Once the fields are computed, it would be easy to verify the correct sign of the phase terms following the procedure outlined in Figure 3 of Herrera and Quinto-Su's manuscript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Structure of the Algorithm&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The algorithm to compute the focus fields will proceed as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(optional) Propgate the inputs fields from the AS to the back principal plane using paraxial wave propagation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Input the sampled fields in the back principal plane in the \( \left( x_{\infty}, y_{\infty} \right) \) coordinate system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transform the fields to the \( \left( k_x, k_y \right) \) coordinate system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compute the fields in the \( \left(x, y, z \right) \) coordinate system using the FFT&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Additional Remarks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Zero padding the mesh will increase the sample space resolution beyond the Abbe limit, but since the fields remain zero outside of the support, no new information is added.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On the other hand, zero padding might be required when computing fields going from the sample space to the back principal plane to faithfully reproduce any evanescent components.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Separating the coordinate system and mesh construction from the calculation of the fields reveals that the two assumptions of the model belong separately to each part. The sine condition is used in the construction of the coordinate systems, whereas energy conservation is used when computing the fields.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This post did not explain how to compute the fields.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Herrera and Quinto-Su (and possibly also Novotny and Hecht) appear to use an "effective" focal length which can be obtained by multiplying the one that I use by the sample space refractive index. I prefer my formulation because it is consistent with geometric optics and the well-known expression for the diameter of an objective's entrance pupil. When the fields are calculated, however, I do not yet know whether the arguments of the phasors of the Debye integral will require modification.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lukas Novotny and Bert Hecht, "Principles of Nano-Optics," Cambridge University Press (2006). &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9780511813535"&gt;https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9780511813535&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/coordinate-systems-for-modeling-microscope-objectives/#fnref:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/coordinate-systems-for-modeling-microscope-objectives/#fnref2:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isael Herrera and Pedro A. Quinto-Su, "Simple computer program to calculate arbitrary tightly focused (propagating and evanescent) vector light fields," arXiv:2211.06725 (2022). &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2211.06725"&gt;https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2211.06725&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/coordinate-systems-for-modeling-microscope-objectives/#fnref:2" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/coordinate-systems-for-modeling-microscope-objectives/#fnref2:2" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/coordinate-systems-for-modeling-microscope-objectives/#fnref3:2" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marcel Leutenegger, Ramachandra Rao, Rainer A. Leitgeb, and Theo Lasser, "Fast focus field calculations," Opt. Express 14, 11277-11291 (2006). &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1364/OE.14.011277"&gt;https://doi.org/10.1364/OE.14.011277&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/coordinate-systems-for-modeling-microscope-objectives/#fnref:3" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sun-Uk Hwang and Yong-Gu Lee, "Simulation of an oil immersion objective lens: A simplified ray-optics model considering Abbe’s sine condition," Opt. Express 16, 21170-21183 (2008). &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1364/OE.16.021170"&gt;https://doi.org/10.1364/OE.16.021170&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/coordinate-systems-for-modeling-microscope-objectives/#fnref:4" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>microscopy</category><category>optics</category><guid>https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/coordinate-systems-for-modeling-microscope-objectives/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 09:52:48 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Mono16 Format and Flir Cameras</title><link>https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/the-mono16-format-and-flir-cameras/</link><dc:creator>Kyle M. Douglass</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;For a long time I had found the Mono16 image format of Flir's cameras a bit strange. In the lab I have several Flir cameras with 12-bit ADC's, but the images they output in Mono16 would span a range from 0 to around 65535. How does the camera map a 12-bit number to a 16-bit number?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you search for the Mono16 format you will find that it's a padded format. This means that, in the 12-bit ADC example, 4 bits in each pixel are always 0, and the remaining 12 bits represent the pixel's value. But this should mean that we should get pixel values only between 0 and 2^12 - 1, or 4095. So how is it that we can saturate one of these cameras with values near 65535?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today it occurred to me that Flir's Mono16 format might not use all the values in the range [0, 65535]. This is indeed the case, as I show below with an image stack that I acquired from one of these cameras:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="code"&gt;&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sorted_unique_pixels&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;unique&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;images&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;ravel&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;())&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;unique&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;diff&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;sorted_unique_pixels&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;array&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;([&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;16&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="mi"&gt;32&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="mi"&gt;48&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="mi"&gt;64&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="mi"&gt;96&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;144&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;dtype&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;uint16&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This prints all the possible, unique differences between the sorted and flattened pixel values in my particular image stack. Notice how they are all multiples of 16?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's look also at the sorted array of unique values itself:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="code"&gt;&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sorted_unique_pixels&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;array&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;([&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;5808&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="mi"&gt;5824&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="mi"&gt;5856&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;57312&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;57328&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;57472&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;dtype&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;uint16&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are more than a million pixels in this array, yet they all take values that are integer multiples of 16.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It looks like Flir's Mono16 format rescales the camera's output onto the interval [0, 65535] by introducing "gaps" between the numbers equal to 2^16 - 2^N where N is the bit-depth of the camera's ADC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But wait just a moment. Above I said that 4 bits in the Mono16 are zero, but I assumed that these were the most significant bits. If the least significant bits are the zero padding, then the allowed pixel values would be, for example, 
&lt;code&gt;0000 0000 = 0&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;0001 0000 = 16&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;0010 0000 = 32&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;0011 0000 = 48&lt;/code&gt;, etc. (Here I ignored the first 8 bits for clarity.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it appears that Flir is indeed padding the 12-bit ADC data with 0's in its Mono16 format. But, somewhat counter-intuitively, &lt;em&gt;it is the four least significant bits that are the zero padding.&lt;/em&gt; I say this is counter-intuitive because I have another camera that pads the most significant bits, so that the maximum pixel value is really 2^N - 1, with N being the ADC's bit-depth.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>cameras</category><category>computer vision</category><guid>https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/the-mono16-format-and-flir-cameras/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 12:15:36 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Automated Testing of Simulation Code via Hypothesis Testing</title><link>https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/testing-simulation-code/</link><dc:creator>Kyle M. Douglass</dc:creator><description>&lt;h2&gt;Missing a Theory of Testing for Scientific Code&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you search the Internet for resources on the theory of testing code, you will find information about the different types of tests and how to write them. You will also find that it is generally accepted among programmers that good code is tested and bad code is not. The problem for scientists and engineers, however, is that the theory concerning the testing of computer code was developed primarily by programmers that work on systems that model business processes. There is little theory on how, for example, to test the outcome of physics simulations. To further exacerbate the problem, scientific programmers feel obliged to write tests without the guidance of such a theory because of the imperative to test their code. This leads to convoluted tests that are difficult to understand and maintain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Scientific Code is Different&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Code that models business processes is based on explicit rules that are developed from a set of requirements. An example of a rule that a business system might follow is "If a customer has ordered an item and has not paid, then send her an invoice."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To test the above rule, we write out all the possible cases and write a test for each one. For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A customer orders an item without paying. Expected result: an invoice is sent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A customer orders an item and pays at the time of checkout: Expected result: no invoice is sent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have found that a good way to identify test cases in business logic is to look for if/else statements in a rule. Each branch of the statement should be a different test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let's consider a physics simulation. I am an optical engineer, so I will use an example from optics. One thing I have often done in my work is to simulate the image formation process of a lens system, including the noise imparted by the camera. A simple model of a CMOS camera pixel is one that takes an input signal in photons, adds shot noise, converts it to photoelectrons, adds dark noise, and then converts the electron signal into analog-to-digital units. Schematically:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="code"&gt;&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;photons&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;--&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;electrons&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;--&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;ADUs&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A simplified Python code snippet that models this process, including noise, is below. An instance of the camera class has a method called &lt;code&gt;snap&lt;/code&gt; that takes input array of photons and converts it to ADUs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="code"&gt;&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;dataclasses&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;dataclass&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;numpy&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class="nd"&gt;@dataclass&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nc"&gt;Camera&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;baseline&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# ADU&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;bit_depth&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;12&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;dark_noise&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;float&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mf"&gt;6.83&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# e-&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;gain&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;float&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mf"&gt;0.12&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# ADU / e-&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;quantum_efficiency&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;float&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mf"&gt;0.76&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;well_capacity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;32406&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# e-&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;rng&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;random&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Generator&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;random&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;default_rng&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;snap&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="bp"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;signal&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Simulate shot noise and convert to electrons&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;photoelectrons&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="bp"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;rng&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;poisson&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="bp"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;quantum_efficiency&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;signal&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;signal&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;shape&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

        &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Add dark noise&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;electrons&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="bp"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;rng&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;normal&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;scale&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="bp"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;dark_noise&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;photoelectrons&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;shape&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;photoelectrons&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

        &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Clip to the well capacity to model electron saturation&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;electrons&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;clip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;electrons&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="bp"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;well_capacity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

        &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Convert to ADU&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;adu&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;electrons&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="bp"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;gain&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="bp"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;baseline&lt;/span&gt;

        &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Clip to the bit depth to model ADU saturation&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;adu&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;clip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;adu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;**&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="bp"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;bit_depth&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

        &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;adu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;astype&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;uint16&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we test this code? In this case, there are no if/else statements to help us identify test cases. Some possible solutions are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An expert can review it. But what if we don't have an expert? Or, if you are an expert, how do we know that we haven't made a mistake? I have worked professionally as both an optical and a software engineer and I can tell you that I make coding mistakes many times a day. And what if the simulation is thousands of lines of code? This solution, though useful, cannot be sufficient for testing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compute what the results ought to be for a given set of inputs. Rules like "If the baseline is 100, and the bit depth is 12, etc., then the output is 542 ADU" are not that useful here because the output is random.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evaluate the code and manually check that it produces the desired results. This is similar to expert review. The problem with this approach is that you would need to recheck the code every time a change is made. One of the advantages of testing business logic is that the tests can be automated. It would be advantageous to preserve automation in testing scientific code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We could always fix the value of the seed for the random number generator to at least make the test deterministic, but then we would not know whether the variation in the simulation output is what we would expect from run-to-run. I'm also unsure whether the same seed produces the same results across different hardware architectures. Since the simulation is non-deterministic at its core, it would be nice to include this attribute within the test case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Automated Testing of Simulation Results via Hypothesis Testing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The solution that I have found to the above-listed problems is derived from ideas that I learned in a class on quality control that I took in college. In short, we run the simulation a number of times and compute one or more statistics from the results. The statistics are compared to their theoretical values in a hypothesis test, and, if the result is outside of a given tolerance, the test fails. If the probability of failure is made small enough, then a failure of the test &lt;strong&gt;practically&lt;/strong&gt; indicates an error in the simulation code rather than a random failure due to the stochastic output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Theoretical Values for Test Statistics&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the example of a CMOS camera, both the theoretical mean and the variance of a pixel are known. The &lt;a href="https://www.emva.org/standards-technology/emva-1288/"&gt;EMVA 1288 Linear Model&lt;/a&gt; states that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \mu_y = K \left( \eta \mu_p + \mu_d \right) + B $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where \( \mu_y \) is the mean ADU count, \( K \) is the gain, \( \eta \) is the quantum efficiency, \( \mu_p \) is the mean photon count, \( \mu_d \) is the mean dark noise, and \( B \) is the baseline value, i.e. the average ADU count under no illumination. Likewise, the variance of the pixel describes the noise:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \sigma_y = \sqrt{K^2 \sigma_d^2 + \sigma_q^2 + K \left( \mu_y - B \right)} $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where \( \sigma_y \) is the standard deviation of the ADU counts, \( \sigma_d^2 \) is the dark noise variance, and \( \sigma_q^2 = 1 / 12 \, \text{ADU} \) is the quantization noise, i.e. the noise from converting an analog voltage into discrete ADU values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Hypothesis Testing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can formulate a hypothesis test for each test statistic. The test for each is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Null hypothesis :&lt;/strong&gt; the simulation statistics and the theoretical values are the same&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alternative hypothesis :&lt;/strong&gt; the simulation statistics and the theoretical values are different&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's first focus on the mean pixel values. To perform this hypothesis test, I ran the simulation code a number of times. For convenience, I chose an input signal of 1000 photons. Here's the resulting histogram:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://kylemdouglass.com/images/camera-mean-adus.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mean of this distribution is 190.721 ADU and the standard deviation is 3.437 ADU. The theoretical values are 191.2 ADU and 3.420 ADU, respectively. Importantly, if I re-run the simulation, then I get a different histogram because the simulation's output is random.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above histogram is called the &lt;strong&gt;sampling distribution of the mean&lt;/strong&gt;, and its width is proportional to the &lt;strong&gt;standard error of the mean&lt;/strong&gt;. (&lt;em&gt;Edit 2024/05/30&lt;/em&gt; Actually, I think I am wrong here. This is not the sampling distribution of the mean. To get it we would need to repeat the above experiment a number of times and compute the mean each time, much like I do in the following section. The set of all means from doing so would be its sampling distribution. Fortunately, the estimate of the confidence intervals in what follows should still hold because the sampling distribution of the mean tends to a normal distribution for large \(N \), and this allows for the expression in the equation that follows.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Hypothesis Testing of the Mean Pixel Value&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To perform the hypthosesis test on the mean, I build a confidence interval around the simulated value using the following formula:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \mu_y \pm X \frac{s}{\sqrt{N}} $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here \( s \) is my estimated standard deviation (3.437 ADU in the example above), and \( N = 10,000 \) is the number of simulated values. Their ratio \( \frac{s}{\sqrt{N}} \) is an estimate of the &lt;strong&gt;standard error of the mean&lt;/strong&gt;. \( X \) is a proportionality factor that is essentially a tolerance on how close the simulated value must be to the theoretical one to be considered "equal". A larger tolerance means that it is less likely that the hypothesis test will fail, but I am less certain that the value of the simulation is exactly equal to the theoretical value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this looks familiar, it should. In introductory statistics classes, this approach is called &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Student%27s_t-test"&gt;Student's one sample t-test&lt;/a&gt;. In the t-test, the value for \( X \) is denoted as \( t \) and depends on the desired confidence level and on the number of data points in the sample. (Strictly speaking, it's the number of data points minus 1.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far as I can tell there's no rule for selecting a value of \( X \); rather, it's a free parameter. I often choose 3. Why? Well, if the sampling distribution is approximately normally distributed, and the number of sample points is large, then the theoretical mean should lie within 3 standard errors of the simulated one approximately 99.7% of the time &lt;strong&gt;if the algorithm is correct.&lt;/strong&gt; Alternatively, this means that a correct simulation will produce a result that is more than three standard errors from the theoretical mean about every 1 out of 370 test runs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Hypothesis Testing of the Noise&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recall that standard deviation of pixel values is a measure of the noise. The approach to testing it remains the same as before. We write the confidence interval as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \sigma_y \pm X \left( s.e. \right) $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where we have \( s.e. \) as the standard error of the standard deviation. If the simulated standard deviation is outside this interval, then we reject the null hypothesis and fail the test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, how do we calculate the standard error of the standard deviation? Unlike with the mean value, we have only one value for the standard deviation of the pixel values. Furthermore, there doesn't seem to be a simple formula for the standard error of the variance or standard error of the standard deviation. (I looked around the Math and Statistics Stack Exchanges, but what I did find produced standard errors that were way too large.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Faced with this problem, I have two options:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;run the simulation a number of times to get a distribution of standard deviations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;draw pixel values from the existing simulation data &lt;strong&gt;with replacement&lt;/strong&gt; to estimate the sampling distribution. This approach is known as &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bootstrapping_(statistics)"&gt;bootstrapping&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this situation, both are valid approaches because the simulation runs quite quickly. However, if the simulation is slow, bootstrapping might be desirable because resampling the simulated data is relatively fast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I provide below a function that makes a bootstrap estimate of the standard error of pixel values to give you an idea of how this works. It draws &lt;code&gt;n&lt;/code&gt; samples from the simulated pixel values with replacement and places the results in the rows of an array. Then, the standard devation of each row is computed. Finally, since the standard error is the standard deviation of the sampling distribution, the standard deviation of resampled standard deviations is computed and returned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="code"&gt;&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;se_std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;n&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;float&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;samples&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;random&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;choice&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;ravel&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;replace&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kc"&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;std_sampling_distribution&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;samples&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;axis&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;std_sampling_distribution&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the value of &lt;code&gt;n&lt;/code&gt; in the function above is arbitrary. From what I can tell, setting &lt;code&gt;n&lt;/code&gt; to be the size of the data is somewhat standard practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Automated Hypothesis Testing&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, we can calculate the probability that the mean and standard deviation of the simulated pixel values will lie farther than some distance from their theoretical values. This means that we know roughly how often a test will fail due to pure luck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To put these into an automated test function, we need only translate the two hypotheses into an assertion. The null hypothesis should correspond to the argument of the assertion being true; the alternative hypothesis corresponds to a false argument.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="code"&gt;&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;TOL&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;test_cmos_camera&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;camera&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;num_pixels&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;32&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;32&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;mean_photons&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;photons&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;mean_photons&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;ones&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;num_pixels&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;astype&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;uint8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;expected_mean&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mf"&gt;191.2&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;expected_std&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mf"&gt;3.42&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="n"&gt;img&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;camera&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;snap&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;photons&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="n"&gt;tol_mean&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;TOL&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;img&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;sqrt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;num_pixels&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;num_pixels&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;])&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;tol_std&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;TOL&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;se_std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;img&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="k"&gt;assert&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;isclose&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;img&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;mean&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;expected_mean&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;atol&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;tol_mean&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;assert&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;isclose&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;img&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;expected_std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;atol&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;tol_std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a &lt;code&gt;TOL&lt;/code&gt; value of 3 and with the sampling distributions being more-or-less normally distributed, each assertion should fail about 1 / 370 times because the area in the tails of the distribution beyond three standard errors is 1 / 370. We can put this test into our test suite and continuous integration (CI) system and run it automatically using whatever tools we wish, e.g. GitHub Actions and pytest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Discussion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Non-deterministic Tests&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is an often-stated rule of thumb that automated tests should never fail randomly because it makes failures difficult to diagnose and makes you likely to ignore the tests. Here however it is in the very nature of this test that it will fail randomly from time to time. What are we to do?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An easy solution would be to isolate these sorts of tests and run them separately from the deterministic ones so that we know exactly where the error occurred. Then, if there is a failure of the non-deterministic tests, the CI could just run them again. If &lt;code&gt;TOL&lt;/code&gt; is set so that a test failure is very rare, then any failure of these tests twice would practically indicate a failure of the algorithm to produce the theoretical results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Testing Absolute Tolerances&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It could be argued that what I presented here is a lot of work just to make an assertion that a simulation result is close to a known value. In other words, it's just a fancy way to test for absolute tolerances, and possibly is more complex than it needs to be. I can't say that I entirely disagree with this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an alternative, consider the following: if we run the simulation a few times we can get a sense of the variation in its output, and we can use these values to roughly set a tolerance that states by how much the simulated and theoretical results should differ. This is arguably faster than constructing the confidence intervals like we did above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The value in the hypothesis testing approach is that you can know the probability of failure to a high degree of accuracy. Whether or not this is important probably depends on what you want to do, but it does provide you with a deeper understanding of the behavior of the simulation that might help debug difficult problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Testing for Other Types of Errors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are certainly other problems in testing simulation code that are not covered here. The above approach won't tell you directly if you have entered an equation incorrectly. It also requires theoretical values for the summary statistics of the simulation's output. If you have a theory for these already, you might argue that a simulation would be superfluous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it's easy to implement automated tests for your simulation that are based on hypothesis testing, and if you expect the code to change often, then having a few of these sorts of tests will at least provide you a degree of confidence that everything is working as you expect as you make changes. And that is one of the goals of having automated tests: fearless refactoring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Testing the Frequency of Failures&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I stated often that with hypothesis testing we know how often the code should fail, but we never actually tested that. We could have run the simulation a large number of times and verified that the number of failures was approximately equal to the theoretical number of failures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To my mind, it seems that this is just the exact same problem that was addressed above, but instead of testing summary statistics on the output values we test the number of failures. And since the number of failures will vary randomly, we would need a sampling distribution for this. So really this approach requires more CPU clock cycles to do the same thing because we need to run the simulation a large number of times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automated testing of simulation code is different than testing business logic due to its stochastic nature and inability to be reduced to "rules"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We can formulate hypothesis tests to determine how often the simulation produces values that are farther than a given distance from what theory predicts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The hypothesis tests can be translated into test cases: accepting the null hypothesis means the test passes, whereas rejecting the null hypothesis means the test fails&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Non-deterministic testing is useful when it is quick to implement and you expect to change the code often&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description><category>cameras</category><category>simulation</category><category>statistics</category><guid>https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/testing-simulation-code/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 21 May 2024 07:54:40 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Simple Object-Space Telecentric System</title><link>https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/a-simple-object-space-telecentric-system/</link><dc:creator>Kyle M. Douglass</dc:creator><description>&lt;h2&gt;Object-space telecentricity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been working on a software package recently for optical systems design. The process of building the package has proceeded like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Think of a particular case that I want to model; for example an infinite conjugate afocal system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Implement it in the code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discover that the code doesn't work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a test case that helps debug the code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Repeat&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am modeling a telecentric lens in the current iteration of this loop. To keep things simple, I am limiting myself to an &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Telecentric_lens#Object-space_telecentric_lenses"&gt;object-space telecentric system&lt;/a&gt;. This was more challenging than I expected. In part, the reason is that I was trying to infer whether a system was or was not telecentric from the lens prescription data and a ray trace, which has two problems:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I need to do a floating point comparison between two numbers to say whether a system is telecentric. Either the chief ray angle in object-space has to be zero or the entrance pupil must be located at infinity. Floating point comparisons are notoriously difficult to get right, and if you're doing them then you might want to rethink what you're trying to model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Numerous checks are needed before we can even trace any rays. For example, I should check first whether the user placed the object at infinity. This would form the image in the same plane as the aperture stop, which does not really make sense.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find it interesting that &lt;a href="https://support.zemax.com/hc/en-us/articles/1500005488201-Modeling-a-lens-that-is-telecentric-in-image-space"&gt;Zemax addresses these problems&lt;/a&gt; by introducing object-space telecentricity as an extra boolean flag that forces the chief ray angle to be zero in the object-space. In other words, the user needs to know what they're doing and to specify that they want telecentricity from the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;An object-space telecentric example&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I adapted the following example from lens data presented in this video: &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JfstTsuNAz0"&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JfstTsuNAz0&lt;/a&gt;. Notably, the object distance was increased by nearly a factor of two from what was given in the video so that the image plane was at a finite distance from the lens. Paraxial ray trace results were computed by hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table border="1"&gt;
    &lt;caption&gt;
        A simple object-space telecentric system comprising a planoconvex lens and a stop.
    &lt;/caption&gt;
    &lt;thead&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;th scope="row"&gt;Surface&lt;/th&gt;
            &lt;th&gt;0&lt;/th&gt;
            &lt;th&gt;1&lt;/th&gt;
            &lt;th&gt;2&lt;/th&gt;
            &lt;th&gt;3&lt;/th&gt;
            &lt;th&gt;4&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/thead&gt;
    &lt;tbody&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;th scope="row"&gt;Comment&lt;/th&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;OBJ&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;STOP&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;IMG&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/tbody&gt;
    &lt;tbody&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;th scope="row"&gt;\( R \)&lt;/th&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;\( \infty \)&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;-9.750&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;th scope="row"&gt;\( t \)&lt;/th&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;29.4702&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;15.97699&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;17.323380&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;th scope="row"&gt;\( n \)&lt;/th&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;1.610248&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/tbody&gt;
    &lt;tbody&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;th scope="row"&gt;\( C \)&lt;/th&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;-0.10256&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
         &lt;/tr&gt; 
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;th scope="row"&gt;\( -\Phi \)&lt;/th&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;-0.06259&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;th scope="row"&gt;\( t/n \)&lt;/th&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;29.4702&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;1.24204&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;15.97699&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;17.323380&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/tbody&gt;
    &lt;tbody&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;th scope="row"&gt;\( y \)&lt;/th&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;29.4702&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;30.712240&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;15.97699&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;th scope="row"&gt;\( nu \)&lt;/th&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;-0.922279&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;-0.922279&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/tbody&gt;
    &lt;tbody&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;th scope="row"&gt;\( \bar{y} \)&lt;/th&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;-1.084270&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;th scope="row"&gt;\( n \bar{u} \)&lt;/th&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;-0.06259&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;-0.06259&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This system is shown below with lens semi-diameters of 5 mm. Note that the stop is at the paraxial focus of the lens. The rays in the sketch cross the axis before the stop because of spherical aberration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;svg viewbox="0, 0, 1344, 150" width="120%" fill="none" stroke="black" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"&gt;&lt;path d="M 632.646354675293 142.5 L 632.646354675293 142.5 L 632.646354675293 142.5 L 632.646354675293 135.39473819732666 L 632.646354675293 128.2894731760025 L 632.646354675293 121.18420815467834 L 632.646354675293 114.078946352005 L 632.646354675293 106.97368454933167 L 632.646354675293 99.86841952800751 L 632.646354675293 92.76315450668335 L 632.646354675293 85.65789270401001 L 632.646354675293 78.55263090133667 L 632.646354675293 71.44736909866333 L 632.646354675293 64.34210085868835 L 632.646354675293 57.236839056015015 L 632.646354675293 50.131577253341675 L 632.646354675293 43.0263090133667 L 632.646354675293 35.92104721069336 L 632.646354675293 28.81578540802002 L 632.646354675293 21.71052360534668 L 632.646354675293 14.60526180267334 L 632.646354675293 7.5 L 632.646354675293 7.5 L 641.0208705067635 7.5 L 641.0208705067635 7.5 L 644.972696185112 14.60526180267334 L 648.3765449523926 21.71052360534668 L 651.27783036232 28.81578540802002 L 653.7113556861877 35.92104721069336 L 655.7038663029671 43.0263090133667 L 657.275763630867 50.131577253341675 L 658.4422525763512 57.236839056015015 L 659.2141510248184 64.34210085868835 L 659.5984016060829 71.44736909866333 L 659.5984016060829 78.55263090133667 L 659.2141510248184 85.65789270401001 L 658.4422541856766 92.76315450668335 L 657.275763630867 99.86841952800751 L 655.7038679122925 106.97368454933167 L 653.7113556861877 114.078946352005 L 651.2778335809708 121.18420815467834 L 648.3765481710434 128.2894731760025 L 644.972696185112 135.39473819732666 L 641.0208705067635 142.5 L 641.0208705067635 142.5 L 632.646354675293 142.5 Z" stroke="black" stroke-width="1" stroke-linejoin="bevel" fill="none"&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;path d="M 632.646354675293 142.5 L 632.646354675293 142.5 L 632.646354675293 135.39473819732666 L 632.646354675293 128.2894731760025 L 632.646354675293 121.18420815467834 L 632.646354675293 114.078946352005 L 632.646354675293 106.97368454933167 L 632.646354675293 99.86841952800751 L 632.646354675293 92.76315450668335 L 632.646354675293 85.65789270401001 L 632.646354675293 78.55263090133667 L 632.646354675293 71.44736909866333 L 632.646354675293 64.34210085868835 L 632.646354675293 57.236839056015015 L 632.646354675293 50.131577253341675 L 632.646354675293 43.0263090133667 L 632.646354675293 35.92104721069336 L 632.646354675293 28.81578540802002 L 632.646354675293 21.71052360534668 L 632.646354675293 14.60526180267334 L 632.646354675293 7.5" stroke="black" stroke-width="1" stroke-linejoin="miter" fill="none"&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;path d="M 875.3357162475586 142.5 L 875.3357162475586 142.5 L 875.3357162475586 81.75" stroke="black" stroke-width="1" stroke-linejoin="miter" fill="none"&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;path d="M 875.3357162475586 68.25 L 875.3357162475586 68.25 L 875.3357162475586 7.5" stroke="black" stroke-width="1" stroke-linejoin="miter" fill="none"&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;path d="M 641.0208705067635 142.5 L 641.0208705067635 142.5 L 644.972696185112 135.39473819732666 L 648.3765481710434 128.2894731760025 L 651.2778335809708 121.18420815467834 L 653.7113556861877 114.078946352005 L 655.7038679122925 106.97368454933167 L 657.275763630867 99.86841952800751 L 658.4422541856766 92.76315450668335 L 659.2141510248184 85.65789270401001 L 659.5984016060829 78.55263090133667 L 659.5984016060829 71.44736909866333 L 659.2141510248184 64.34210085868835 L 658.4422525763512 57.236839056015015 L 657.275763630867 50.131577253341675 L 655.7038663029671 43.0263090133667 L 653.7113556861877 35.92104721069336 L 651.27783036232 28.81578540802002 L 648.3765449523926 21.71052360534668 L 644.972696185112 14.60526180267334 L 641.0208705067635 7.5" stroke="black" stroke-width="1" stroke-linejoin="miter" fill="none"&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;path d="M 1109.2013397216797 142.5 L 1109.2013397216797 142.5 L 1109.2013397216797 135.39473819732666 L 1109.2013397216797 128.2894731760025 L 1109.2013397216797 121.18420815467834 L 1109.2013397216797 114.078946352005 L 1109.2013397216797 106.97368454933167 L 1109.2013397216797 99.86841952800751 L 1109.2013397216797 92.76315450668335 L 1109.2013397216797 85.65789270401001 L 1109.2013397216797 78.55263090133667 L 1109.2013397216797 71.44736909866333 L 1109.2013397216797 64.34210085868835 L 1109.2013397216797 57.236839056015015 L 1109.2013397216797 50.131577253341675 L 1109.2013397216797 43.0263090133667 L 1109.2013397216797 35.92104721069336 L 1109.2013397216797 28.81578540802002 L 1109.2013397216797 21.71052360534668 L 1109.2013397216797 14.60526180267334 L 1109.2013397216797 7.5" stroke="#999999" stroke-width="1" stroke-linejoin="miter" fill="none"&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;path d="M 234.7986602783203 142.5 L 234.7986602783203 142.5 L 234.7986602783203 135.39473819732666 L 234.7986602783203 128.2894731760025 L 234.7986602783203 121.18420815467834 L 234.7986602783203 114.078946352005 L 234.7986602783203 106.97368454933167 L 234.7986602783203 99.86841952800751 L 234.7986602783203 92.76315450668335 L 234.7986602783203 85.65789270401001 L 234.7986602783203 78.55263090133667 L 234.7986602783203 71.44736909866333 L 234.7986602783203 64.34210085868835 L 234.7986602783203 57.236839056015015 L 234.7986602783203 50.131577253341675 L 234.7986602783203 43.0263090133667 L 234.7986602783203 35.92104721069336 L 234.7986602783203 28.81578540802002 L 234.7986602783203 21.71052360534668 L 234.7986602783203 14.60526180267334 L 234.7986602783203 7.5" stroke="#999999" stroke-width="1" stroke-linejoin="miter" fill="none"&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;path d="M 234.7986602783203 115.5 L 234.7986602783203 115.5 L 632.646354675293 115.5 L 653.2606882452965 115.5 L 875.3357162475586 69.18727111816406 L 1109.2013397216797 20.41567325592041" stroke="red" stroke-width="0.5" stroke-linejoin="miter" fill="none"&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;path d="M 234.7986602783203 75 L 234.7986602783203 75 L 632.646354675293 75 L 659.646354675293 75 L 875.3357162475586 75 L 1109.2013397216797 75" stroke="red" stroke-width="0.5" stroke-linejoin="miter" fill="none"&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;path d="M 234.7986602783203 34.5 L 234.7986602783203 34.5 L 632.646354675293 34.5 L 653.2606882452965 34.5 L 875.3357162475586 80.81272888183594 L 1109.2013397216797 129.5843267440796" stroke="red" stroke-width="0.5" stroke-linejoin="miter" fill="none"&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;path d="M 234.7986602783203 2451228.234375 L 234.7986602783203 2451228.234375 L 632.646354675293 2451193.4296875" stroke="red" stroke-width="0.5" stroke-linejoin="miter" fill="none"&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;path d="M 234.7986602783203 2451187.734375 L 234.7986602783203 2451187.734375 L 632.646354675293 2451152.9296875" stroke="red" stroke-width="0.5" stroke-linejoin="miter" fill="none"&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;path d="M 234.7986602783203 2451147.234375 L 234.7986602783203 2451147.234375 L 632.646354675293 2451112.4296875" stroke="red" stroke-width="0.5" stroke-linejoin="miter" fill="none"&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Remarks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Marginal ray trace&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first the marginal ray trace was a bit confusing because the entrance pupil is at infinity. How can the marginal ray, which intersects the pupil at its edge, be traced when the pupil is at infinity? Then I remembered that I don't aim for the edge of the pupil when tracing the marginal ray. Instead, I launch a ray from the axis in the object plane at a random angle taking the surface with the smallest ray height as the aperture stop. (I chose a paraxial angle of 1 in the table above. Technically, this is called a pseudo-marginal ray. The real marginal ray is calculated from it by rescaling the surface intersection heights by the aperture stop semi-diameter.) Once you have the marginal ray in image space, just find its intersection with the axis to determine the image location.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Telecentric lens design&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how would an object-space telecentric design be implemented in software? First, I'd set an option that would force the chief ray angle to 0 in the object space. Then, I'd simply place a solve on the aperture stop that puts it at the location where the chief ray intersects the axis.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>ray tracing</category><category>telecentricity</category><guid>https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/a-simple-object-space-telecentric-system/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 11 Mar 2024 07:59:17 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Fusion 360 Core Concepts</title><link>https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/fusion-360-core-concepts/</link><dc:creator>Kyle M. Douglass</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I decided recently to learn Fusion 360 to help with some custom optomechanical designs that I need in the lab. The following are my notes about its core concepts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Assemblies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An assembly is a group of parts in one design file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In CAD, there are two ways to create assemblies:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bottom-up&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create parts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add parts to the assembly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Top-down&lt;/strong&gt; (used by Fusion 360)&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start with an assembly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add parts to it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bodies vs. components&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Bodies&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A body is a 3D shape used to add or remove components.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two core types:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Solid bodies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Surface bodies (denoted by a yellow face)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other types include T-Splines (created in the Form environment) used to create freeform shapes, and mesh bodies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bodies must be of the same type to interact with one another.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Components&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A component is a part or "container" used within an assembly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Components can contain&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bodies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;construction planes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sketches&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;canvases&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;origin planes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;other components (a.k.a. &lt;strong&gt;subassemblies&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Joints&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joints are how components are forced to stay together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Guidelines&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Always start an assembly with a new component&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Always rename components and bodies right after creation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TzG2deElWqI&amp;amp;t=0s"&gt;Bodies vs Components&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description><category>cad</category><guid>https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/fusion-360-core-concepts/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2024 14:16:22 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>