<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Kyle M. Douglass (Posts about microscopy)</title><link>https://kylemdouglass.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://kylemdouglass.com/categories/microscopy.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2025 &lt;a href="mailto:kyle.m.douglass@gmail.com"&gt;Kyle M. Douglass&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Creative Commons License BY-NC-SA"
style="border-width:0; margin-bottom:12px;"
src="https://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-sa/4.0/88x31.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Jun 2025 13:55:26 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Why is Camera Read Noise Gaussian Distributed?</title><link>https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/why-is-camera-read-noise-gaussian-distributed/</link><dc:creator>Kyle M. Douglass</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;As a microscopist I work with very weak light signals, often just tens of photons per camera pixel. As a result, the images I record are noisy&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/why-is-camera-read-noise-gaussian-distributed/#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. To a good approximation, the value of a pixel is a sum of two random variables describing two different physical processes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;photon shot noise, which is described by a Poisson probability mass function, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;camera read noise, which is described by a Gaussian probability density function.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read noise has units of electrons, which must be discrete, positive integers. So why is it modeled as a continuous probability density function&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/why-is-camera-read-noise-gaussian-distributed/#fn:2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Source(s) of Read Noise&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Janesick&lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/why-is-camera-read-noise-gaussian-distributed/#fn:3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; defines read noise as "any noise source that is not a function of signal." This means that there is not necessarily one single source of read noise. It is commonly understood that it comes from somewhere in the camera electronics, but "somewhere" need not imply that it is isolated to one location.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The signal from a camera pixel is the number of photoelectrons that were generated inside the pixel. I imagine readout of this signal as a linear path consisting of many steps. The signal might change form along this path, such as going from number of electrons to a voltage. At each step, there is a small probability that some small error is added to (or maybe also removed from?) the signal. The final result is a value that differs randomly from the original signal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Importantly, I do not think that it matters which physical process each step actually represents; rather there just has to be many of them for this abstraction to be valid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Read Noise is Gaussian because of the Central Limit Theorem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason for my conclusion that we can ignore the details so long as there are many steps is the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can model the error introduced by each step as a random variable. Let's assume that each step is independent of the others. The result of camera readout is a sum of a large number of independent random variables. And of course the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Central_limit_theorem"&gt;Central Limit Theorem&lt;/a&gt; states that the distribution of the sum of random variables tends towards a normal distribution, i.e. Gaussian, as the number of random variables tends towards infinity. This happens regardless of the distributions of the underlying random variables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So read noise can appear to be effectively Gaussian so long as there are many steps along the path of conversion from photoelectrons to pixel values and each step has a chance of introducing an error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Sums of Discrete Random Variables&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I encountered one conceptual difficulty here: the sum of discrete random variables is still discrete. If I have several variables that produce only integers, their sum is still an integer. I cannot get, say, 3.14159 as a result. Does the Gaussian approximation, which is for continuous random variables, still apply in this case?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This question is relevant because the signal in a camera is transformed between discrete a continuous representations at least twice: from electrons to voltage and from voltage to analog-to-digital units (ADUs).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's say that I have a discrete random variable that can assume values of 0 or 1, and the probability that the value is 1 is denoted \( p \). This is known as a Bernoulli trial. Now let's say that I have a large number \( n \) of Bernoulli trials. But the sum of \( n \) Bernoulli trials has a distribution that is binomial, and this is well-known to be approximated as a Gaussian when certain conditions are met, including large \( n \)&lt;sup id="fnref:4"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/why-is-camera-read-noise-gaussian-distributed/#fn:4"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. So a sum of a large number of discrete random variables can have a probability distribution function that is approximated as a Gaussian.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This does not mean that the sum of discrete random variables can take on continuous values.&lt;/strong&gt; Rather, the probability associated with any one output value can be estimated by a Gaussian probability density function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But how exactly can I use a continuous distribution to approximate a discrete one? After all, if the random variable \( Y \) is a continuous, Gaussian random variable, then \(P (Y = a)  = 0 \) for all values of \( a \). To get a non-zero probability from a probability density function, we need to integrate it over some interval of its domain. We can therefore integrate the Gaussian in a small interval around each possible value of the discrete random variable, and then associate this integrated area with the probability of the obtaining that discrete value. This is called a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Continuity_correction"&gt;continuity correction&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Example of a Continuity Correction&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a very simple example, consider a discrete random variable \( X \) that is approximated by a Gaussian continuous random variable \( Y \). The probability of getting a discrete value 5 is \( P (X = 5) \). The Gaussian approximation is \( P ( 4.5 \lt Y \lt 5.5 ) \), i.e. we integrate the Gaussian from 4.5 to 5.5 to compute the approximate probability of getting the discrete value 5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote a blog post about this a while back: &lt;a href="https://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/modeling-noise-for-image-simulations/"&gt;https://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/modeling-noise-for-image-simulations/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/why-is-camera-read-noise-gaussian-distributed/#fnref:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is often asserted without justification. See for example Janesick, Photon Transfer, page 34. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/why-is-camera-read-noise-gaussian-distributed/#fnref:2" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1117/3.725073"&gt;https://doi.org/10.1117/3.725073&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/why-is-camera-read-noise-gaussian-distributed/#fnref:3" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Binomial_distribution#Normal_approximation"&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Binomial_distribution#Normal_approximation&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/why-is-camera-read-noise-gaussian-distributed/#fnref:4" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cameras</category><category>microscopy</category><category>statistics</category><guid>https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/why-is-camera-read-noise-gaussian-distributed/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2025 08:40:12 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Coordinate Systems for Modeling Microscope Objectives</title><link>https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/coordinate-systems-for-modeling-microscope-objectives/</link><dc:creator>Kyle M. Douglass</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;A common model for infinity corrected microscope objectives is that of an aplanatic and telecentric optical system. In many developments of this model, emphasis is placed upon the calculation of the electric field near the focus. However, this has the effect that the definition of the coordinate systems and geometry are conflated with the determination of the fields. In addition, making the model amenable to computation often occurs as an afterthought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post I will explore the geometry of an aplanatic system for modeling high NA objectives with an emphasis on computational implementations. My approach follows Novotny and Hecht&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/coordinate-systems-for-modeling-microscope-objectives/#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and Herrera and Quinto-Su&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/coordinate-systems-for-modeling-microscope-objectives/#fn:2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Model Components&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The model system is illustrated below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src="https://kylemdouglass.com/images/aplanatic-telecentric-system.png"&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A high NA, infinity corrected microscope objective as an aplanatic and telecentric optical system.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this model, we abstract over the details of the objective by representing it as four surfaces:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A back focal plane containing an aperture stop&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A back principal plane, \( P \)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A front principal surface, \( P' \)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A front focal plane&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The space to the left of the back principal plane is called the infinity space. The space to the right of the front principal surface is called the sample space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We let the infinity space refractive index \( n_1 = 1 \) because it is in air. The refractive index \( n_2 \) is the refractive index of the immersion medium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The unit vectors \( \mathbf{n} \) are not used in this discussion; they are relevant for computing the fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Assumptions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We make one assumption: the system obeys the sine condition. The meaning of this will be explained later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An aplanatic system is one that obeys the sine condition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will not assume the intensity law to conserve energy because it is only necessary when computing the electric field near the focus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Aperture Stop and Back Focal Plane&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aperture stop (AS) of an optical system is the element that limits the angle of the marginal ray.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The system is telecentric because the aperture stop is located in the back focal plane (BFP). We can shape the focal field by spatially modulating any of the amplitude, phase, or polarization of the incident light in a plane conjugate to the BFP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Back Principal Plane&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the plane in infinity space at which rays appear to refract. It is a plane because rays coming from a point in the front focal plane all emerge into the infinity space in the same direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strictly speaking, focus field calculations require us to propagate the field from the AS to the back principal plane before computing the Debye diffraction integral, but this step is often omitted&lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/coordinate-systems-for-modeling-microscope-objectives/#fn:3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The assumptions of paraxial optics should hold here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Front Principal Surface&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The front principal surface is the surface at which rays appear to refract in the sample space. It is a surface because&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;this is a non-paraxial system, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;we assumed the sine condition.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sine condition states that refraction of a ray coming from an on-axis point in the front focal plane occurs on a spherical cap centered upon the focal point. The distance from the optical axis of the point of intersection of the ray with the surface is proportional to the sine of the angle that the ray makes with the axis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The principal surface is in the far field of the electric field coming from the focal region. For this reason, we can represent a point on this surface as representing a single ray or a plane wave&lt;sup id="fnref2:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/coordinate-systems-for-modeling-microscope-objectives/#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Front Focal Plane&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This plane is located a distance \( n_2 f \) from the principal surface&lt;sup id="fnref:4"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/coordinate-systems-for-modeling-microscope-objectives/#fn:4"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. It is not at a distance \( f \) from this surface. This is a result of imaging in an immersion medium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Geometry and Coordinate Systems&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Aperture Stop Radius&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aperture stop radius \( R \) corresponds to the distance from the axis to the point where the marginal ray intersects the front prinicpal surface. In the sample space, the marginal ray travels at an angle \( \theta_{max} \) with respect to the axis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under the sine condition, this height is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ R = n_2 f \sin{ \theta_{max} } = f \, \text{NA} $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The right-most expression uses the definition of the numerical aperture \( \text{NA} \equiv n \sin{ \theta_{max} } \).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compare this result to the oft-cited expression for the entrance pupil diameter of an objective lens: \( D = 2 f \, \text{NA} \). They are the same. This makes sense because an entrance pupil is either&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;an image of an aperture stop, or&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a physical stop.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Back Principal Plane&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two independent coordinate systems in the back principal plane:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the spatial coordinate system defining the far field positions \( \left( x_{\infty} , y_{\infty} \right) \), and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the coordinate system of the angular spectrum of plane waves \( \left( k_x, k_y \right) \).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The Far Field Coordinate System&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The far field coordinate system may be written in Cartesian form as \( \left( x_{\infty} , y_{\infty} \right) \). It also has a cylindrical representation as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$\begin{eqnarray}
\rho &amp;amp;=&amp;amp; \sqrt{x_{\infty}^2 + y_{\infty}^2} \\
\phi &amp;amp;=&amp;amp; \arctan \left( \frac{y_{\infty}}{x_{\infty}} \right)
\end{eqnarray}$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cylindrical representation appears to be preferred in textbook developments of the model. The Cartesian representation is likely preferred for computational models because it works naturally with two-dimensional arrays of numbers, and because beam shaping elements such as spatial light modulators are rectangular arrays of pixels&lt;sup id="fnref2:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/coordinate-systems-for-modeling-microscope-objectives/#fn:2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The Angular Spectrum Coordinate System&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each point in the angular spectrum coordinate system represents a plane wave in the sample space that is traveling at an angle \( \theta \) to the axis according to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$\begin{eqnarray}
k_x &amp;amp;=&amp;amp; k \sin \theta \cos \phi \\
k_y &amp;amp;=&amp;amp; k \sin \theta \sin \phi \\
k_z &amp;amp;=&amp;amp; k \cos \theta
\end{eqnarray}$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where \( k = 2 \pi n_2 / \lambda = n_2 k_0 \).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along the y-axis ( \( x_{\infty} = 0 \) ), the maximum value of \( k_y \) is \(n_2 k_0 \sin \theta_{max} = k_0 \, \text{NA} \).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Substitute in the expression \( \text{NA} = R / f \) and we get \(k_{y, max} = k_0 R / f\). But \( R = y_{\infty, max} \). This (and similar reasoning for the x-axis) implies that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$\begin{eqnarray}
k_x &amp;amp;=&amp;amp; k_0 x_{\infty} / f \\
k_y &amp;amp;=&amp;amp; k_0 y_{\infty} / f
\end{eqnarray}$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above equations link the angular spectrum coordinate system to the far field coordinate system. They are no longer independent once \( f \) and \( \lambda \) are specified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Numerical Meshes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are four free parameters for defining the coordinate systems of the numerical meshes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The numerical aperture, \( \text{NA} \)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The wavelength, \( \lambda \)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The focal length, \( f \)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The linear mesh size, \( L \)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is a figure that illustrates the construction of the meshes. Both the far field and angular spectrum coordinate systems are represented by a \( L \times L \) array. \( L = 16 \) in the figure below. In general the value of \( L \) should be a power of 2 to help ensure the efficiency of the Fast Fourier Transform (FFT). By considering only powers of 2, we need only consider arrays of even size as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src="https://kylemdouglass.com/images/pupil-function-simulation-mesh.png"&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A numeric mesh representing the far field and angular spectrum coordinate systems of a microscope objective. Fields are sampled at the center of each mesh pixel.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fields are defined on a region of circular support that is centered on this array. The radius of the domain of the far field coordinate system is \( f \text{NA} \); the radius of the domain of the angular spectrum coordinate system is \( k_0 \text{NA} \).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The boxes that are bound by the gray lines indicate the location of each field sample. The \( \left( x_{\infty} , y_{\infty} \right) \) and the \( \left( k_x, k_y \right) \) coordinate systems are sampled at the center of each gray box. The origin is therefore not sampled, which will help avoid division by zero errors when the fields are eventually computed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The figure suggests that we could create only one mesh and scale it by either \( f \text{NA} \) or \( k_0 \text{NA} \) depending on which coordinate system we are working with. The normalized coordinates become \( \left( x_{\infty} / \left( f \text{NA} \right), y_{\infty} / \left( f \text{NA} \right) \right) \) and \( \left( k_x / \left( k_0 \text{NA} \right), k_y / \left( k_0 \text{NA} \right) \right) \).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1D Mesh Example&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an example, let \( L = 16 \). To four decimal places, the normalized coordinates are \( -1.0000, -0.8667, \ldots, -0.0667, 0.0667, \ldots, 0.8667, 1.0000 \).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spacing between array elements is \( 2 / \left( L - 1 \right) = 0.1333 \). Note that 0 is not included in the 1D mesh as it goes from -0.0667 to 0.0667.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A 2D mesh is easily constructed from the 1D mesh using tools such as NumPy's &lt;a href="https://numpy.org/doc/stable/reference/generated/numpy.meshgrid.html"&gt;meshgrid&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Back Principal Plane Mesh Spacings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the x-direction, the mesh spacing of the far field coordinate system is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \Delta x_{\infty} = 2 R / \left( L - 1 \right) = 2 f \text{NA} / \left( L - 1 \right) $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the \( k_x \)-direction, the mesh spacing of the angular spectrum coordinate system is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \Delta k_x = 2 k_{max} / \left( L - 1 \right) = 2 k_0 \text{NA} / \left( L - 1 \right) $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note the symmetry between these two expressions. One scales with \( f \text{NA} \) and the other \( k_0 \text{NA} \). Recall that these are free parameters of the model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Sample Space Mesh Spacing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is interesting to compute the spacing between mesh elements \( \Delta x \) in the sample space when the fields are eventually computed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sampling angular frequency in the sample space is \( k_S = 2 \pi / \Delta x \).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Nyquist-Shannon sampling theory states that the maximum informative angular frequency is \( k_{max} = k_S / 2 \).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the previous section, we know that \( k_{max} = \left(L - 1 \right) \Delta k_x / 2 \), and that \( \Delta k_x = 2 k_0 \text{NA} / \left( L - 1 \right) \).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Combining all the previous expressions and simplifying, we get:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$\begin{eqnarray}
k_S &amp;amp;=&amp;amp; 2 k_{max} \\
2 \pi / \Delta x &amp;amp;=&amp;amp; \left(L - 1 \right) \Delta k_x \\
2 \pi / \Delta x &amp;amp;=&amp;amp; \left(L - 1 \right) \left[ 2 k_0 \text{NA} / \left( L - 1 \right) \right] \\
2 \pi / \Delta x &amp;amp;=&amp;amp; \left(L - 1 \right) \left[ 2 \left(2 \pi / \lambda \right) \text{NA} / \left( L - 1 \right) \right]
\end{eqnarray}$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solving the above expression for \( \Delta x \), we arrive at&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \Delta x = \frac{\lambda}{2 \text{NA}} $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;which is of course the Abbe diffraction limit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Effect of not Sampling the Origin&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Herrera and Quinto-Su&lt;sup id="fnref3:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/coordinate-systems-for-modeling-microscope-objectives/#fn:2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; point out that an error will be introduced if we naively apply the FFT to compute the field components in the \( \left( k_x, k_y \right) \) coordinate system because the origin is not sampled, whereas the FFT assumes that we sample the zero frequency component. The effect is that the result of the FFT has a constant phase error that accounts for a half-pixel shift in each direction of the mesh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider again the 1D mesh example with \(L = 16 \): \( -1.0000, -0.8667, \ldots, -0.0667, 0.0667, \ldots, 0.8667, 1.0000 \)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Python and other languages that index arrays starting at 0, the origin is located at \(L / 2 - 0.5 \), i.e. halfway between the samples at index 7 and 8. A lateral shift in Fourier space is equivalent to a phase shift in real space:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \phi_{shift} \left(X, Y \right) =  -j 2 \pi \frac{0.5}{L} X - j 2 \pi \frac{0.5}{L} Y $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where \( X \) and \( Y \) are normalized coordinates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, I am uncertain whether the phasor with the above argument needs to be multiplied or divided with the result of the FFT because 1. there are a few typos in the signs for the coordinate system bounds in the manuscript of Herrera and Quinto-Su, and 2. the correction was developed for use in MATLAB, which indexes arrays starting at 1. Once the fields are computed, it would be easy to verify the correct sign of the phase terms following the procedure outlined in Figure 3 of Herrera and Quinto-Su's manuscript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Structure of the Algorithm&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The algorithm to compute the focus fields will proceed as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(optional) Propgate the inputs fields from the AS to the back principal plane using paraxial wave propagation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Input the sampled fields in the back principal plane in the \( \left( x_{\infty}, y_{\infty} \right) \) coordinate system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transform the fields to the \( \left( k_x, k_y \right) \) coordinate system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compute the fields in the \( \left(x, y, z \right) \) coordinate system using the FFT&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Additional Remarks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Zero padding the mesh will increase the sample space resolution beyond the Abbe limit, but since the fields remain zero outside of the support, no new information is added.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On the other hand, zero padding might be required when computing fields going from the sample space to the back principal plane to faithfully reproduce any evanescent components.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Separating the coordinate system and mesh construction from the calculation of the fields reveals that the two assumptions of the model belong separately to each part. The sine condition is used in the construction of the coordinate systems, whereas energy conservation is used when computing the fields.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This post did not explain how to compute the fields.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Herrera and Quinto-Su (and possibly also Novotny and Hecht) appear to use an "effective" focal length which can be obtained by multiplying the one that I use by the sample space refractive index. I prefer my formulation because it is consistent with geometric optics and the well-known expression for the diameter of an objective's entrance pupil. When the fields are calculated, however, I do not yet know whether the arguments of the phasors of the Debye integral will require modification.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lukas Novotny and Bert Hecht, "Principles of Nano-Optics," Cambridge University Press (2006). &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9780511813535"&gt;https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9780511813535&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/coordinate-systems-for-modeling-microscope-objectives/#fnref:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/coordinate-systems-for-modeling-microscope-objectives/#fnref2:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isael Herrera and Pedro A. Quinto-Su, "Simple computer program to calculate arbitrary tightly focused (propagating and evanescent) vector light fields," arXiv:2211.06725 (2022). &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2211.06725"&gt;https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2211.06725&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/coordinate-systems-for-modeling-microscope-objectives/#fnref:2" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/coordinate-systems-for-modeling-microscope-objectives/#fnref2:2" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/coordinate-systems-for-modeling-microscope-objectives/#fnref3:2" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marcel Leutenegger, Ramachandra Rao, Rainer A. Leitgeb, and Theo Lasser, "Fast focus field calculations," Opt. Express 14, 11277-11291 (2006). &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1364/OE.14.011277"&gt;https://doi.org/10.1364/OE.14.011277&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/coordinate-systems-for-modeling-microscope-objectives/#fnref:3" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sun-Uk Hwang and Yong-Gu Lee, "Simulation of an oil immersion objective lens: A simplified ray-optics model considering Abbe’s sine condition," Opt. Express 16, 21170-21183 (2008). &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1364/OE.16.021170"&gt;https://doi.org/10.1364/OE.16.021170&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/coordinate-systems-for-modeling-microscope-objectives/#fnref:4" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>microscopy</category><category>optics</category><guid>https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/coordinate-systems-for-modeling-microscope-objectives/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 09:52:48 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Literature Review: An Optical Technique for Remote Focusing in Microscopy</title><link>https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/literature-review-an-optical-technique-for-remote-focusing-in-microscopy/</link><dc:creator>Kyle M. Douglass</dc:creator><description>&lt;h4&gt;Citation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.optcom.2007.10.007"&gt;E.J. Botcherby, R. Juškaitis, M.J. Booth, T. Wilson, "An optical technique for remote focusing in microscopy," Optics Communications, Volume 281, Issue 4, 2008, Pages 880-887&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Abstract&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We describe the theory of a new method of optical refocusing that is particularly relevant for confocal and multiphoton microscopy systems. This method avoids the spherical aberration that is common to other optical refocusing systems. We show that aberration-free refocusing can be achieved over an axial scan range of 70 μm for a 1.4 NA objective lens. As refocusing is implemented remotely from the specimen, this method enables high axial scan speeds without mechanical interference between the objective lens and the specimen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reasons for this Review&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am interested in this paper for two reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recent advances in light sheet microscopy have made the theory of remote focusing more relevant than in the past.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The paper presents a simplified theory of imaging by a high numerical aperture (NA) objective that is useful for understanding image formation in microscopes without resorting to the usual (and more complicated) Richards and Wolf description.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Problem Addressed by the Paper&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The introduction lays out the reasons for this paper in a straightforward manner:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The primary bottleneck in 3D microscopy is axial scanning of the sample (what the authors call &lt;strong&gt;refocusing&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Due to fundamental optics, refocusing a high resolution microscope involves varying the objective/sample distance, i.e. the image plane must remain fixed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It would be desirable to develop a &lt;strong&gt;simple&lt;/strong&gt; mechanism whereby the objective or sample need not move to achieve refocusing in such microscopes without introducing unwanted aberrations.&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is because samples are becoming more complex (think embryos, organoids, etc.).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adaptive optics to fix these aberrations would introduce too much complexity into the setup. (More on this later.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Theory of 3D Imaging in Microscopes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The theory of 3D imaging is introduced by first considering a perfect imaging system with an object space refractive index of \( n_1 \) and an image space refractive index of \( n_2 \). Such a system transforms all the rays emanating from any point in the 3D object space to converge to a single point in the 3D image space. An image formed by such a system is known as a &lt;strong&gt;stigmatic&lt;/strong&gt; image. Unfortunately, Maxwell, followed by Born and Wolf, showed that such a system is only possible if the magnification is the same in all directions and with magnitude&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \left| M \right| = \frac{n_1}{n_2} $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This also implies that conjugate rays must have the same angle with respect to the optical axis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \gamma_2 = \pm \gamma_1 $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any system that does not meet these criteria is not a perfect imaging system. However, there exist some conditions whereby the system can create a perfect image if their requirements are satisfied. Under these conditions, a perfect image will be created only for objects of limited extent in the object space. The two conditions that are relevant for microscopy are&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the sine condition, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the Herschel condition.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under the sine condition, points in a plane transverse to the optical axis are imaged perfectly onto the image plane; points that lie at some axial distance from the object plane suffer from spherical aberration and their images are not stigmatic. In some sense, the Herschel condition is the opposite: on-axis points are imaged stigmatically regardless of their axial position, but off-axis points suffer from aberrations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors note the important fact that most microscope objectives are designed to satisfy the sine condition. As a result, the image plane must remain fixed so that aberration-free refocusing can only be achieved by varying the sample-objective distance. In the authors' words:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...it is possible to see why commercial microscopes, operating under the sine condition refocus by changing the distance between the specimen and objective, as any attempt to detect images away from the optimal image plane will lead to a degradation by spherical aberration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Questions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does an ideal imaging system need only produce stigmatic images, or must it also accurately reproduce the relative positions between any pair of points in the image space (up to a proportionality factor)? &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What exactly are the defintions of the sine and Herschel conditions? Is it the equations relating the angles of conjugate rays? Is it based on the subset of the object space that is imaged stigmatically? Or, as we'll see in the next section, are they defined by the mapping of ray heights between principal surfaces? The authors present a few attributes of each condition, but I'm not certain which attributes serve as the definitions and which are consequences of their assumptions being true.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The General Pupil Function&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really liked this section. The authors present a model of a high NA microscope objective that is based on its principal surfaces. They then use a mix of scalar wave theory and ray tracing to explain why the sine condition produces stigmatic images for points near the axis in the focal plane of the objective. I think the value in this model is that it is much more approachable than the electromagnetic Richards and Wolf model for aplanatic systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To recall, the principal planes in paraxial optics are used to abstract away the details of a lens system. Refraction effectively occurs at these planes, and the focal length is measured relative to them. In non-paraxial systems, the principal planes actually become curved surfaces. Interestingly, most of the famous optics texts, such as Born and Wolf, are somewhat quiet about this fact, but it can be found in papers such as &lt;a href="https://opg.optica.org/opn/abstract.cfm?uri=opn-9-2-56"&gt;Mansuripur, Optics and Photonics News, 9, 56-60 (1998)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So a high NA objective is modeled as a pair of principal surfaces:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The first is a sphere centered on the axis with a radius of curvature equal to the focal distance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The second is a plane perpendicular to the axis, and they refer to it as the pupil plane&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another important thing to note is that these surfaces &lt;strong&gt;are not&lt;/strong&gt; the usual reference spheres centered about object and image points and located in the entrance/exit pupils. I think the authors are right to use principal surfaces because many modern objectives are object-space telecentric, which places the entrance pupil at infinity. In this case the concept of a reference sphere sitting in the entrance pupil becomes a bit murky and I do not know whether it's applicable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, the authors compute the path length differences between points in the object space in this system and use the sine and Herschel conditions to map the rays from the object to the image space principal surfaces. (Each condition results in a different mapping.) Under the approximation that the extent of the object is small, the equations for the path length differences demonstrate what was stated in the previous section: that the sine condition leads to spherical aberration for points that do not lie in the focal plane of the objective. In fact, the phase profile of the wave (the authors weave between ray and wave optics) exiting the second principal plane is expanded as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ znk \left[ 1 - \frac{\rho^2 \sin^2 \alpha}{2} + \frac{\rho^4 \sin^4 \alpha}{8} + \cdots \right] $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For \( z = 0 \), i.e. the object is in the focal plane, all the terms disappear and we get a flat exit wave. When \( z \neq 0 \):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Focussing the tube lens is accurately described by the quadratic term, as it operates in the paraxial regime. Unfortunately the higher order terms which represent spherical aberrations cannot be focussed by the tube lens and consequently there is a breakdown of stigmatic imaging for these points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, &lt;strong&gt;under the sine condition, object points that are outside the focal plane produce curved, non-spherical wavefronts that cannot be focussed to a single point by a tube lens.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If, however, another lens in a reversed orientation was placed so that the curved wavefront from the objective was input into it, it would form a stigmatic image in its image space. This suggests a method for remote focussing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Questions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is the second principal surface flat because the image is formed at infinity by a high NA, infinity-corrected objective? What would its radius of curvature be in a finite conjugate objective?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is the authors' pupil plane coplanar with the objective's exit pupil? Probably not; I think they're referring to the plane in which we find the objective's pupil function, which is somewhat standard (and confusing) nomenclature in microscopy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A Technique for Remote Focusing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We arrive now at the crux of the paper. The authors suggest a setup for remote focusing that is free (within limits) of the spherical aberration that is introduced by objectives that satisfy the sine condition. Effectively they image the pupil from one objective onto the other with a 4f system. This ensures that the aberrated wavefront from the first objective is "unaberrated" by the second objective. Then, another microscope images the focal region of the second objective. 3D scanning is achieved by moving the objective of the second microscope (often called O3 in light sheet microscopes).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few important points:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A 4f system needs to be used between the first (O1) and second (O2) objectives to relay the pupil because it faithfully maps the wavefront without adding any additional phase distortion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On a related note, you can't use tube lenses in the 4f system that are not afocal with the objective. These so-called widefield tube lenses do not share a focal plane with the objective. The objective's pupil must be in the front focal plane of the 4f system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The "perfect" imaging system of O1/4f system/O2 will have an isotropic magnification of \( n1 / n2 \). This satisfies Maxwell's requirement for 3D stigmatic imaging.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This approach will not work well for objectives that require specific tube lenses for aberration correction. (Sorry Zeiss.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will not lose resolution as long as the second objective has a higher &lt;em&gt;angular aperture&lt;/em&gt; (not numerical aperture). You can, for example, use a NA 1.4 oil objective for O1 and a NA 0.95 dry objective for O2 because the O2 object space is in air, whereas the O1 object space is in oil with \( n \approx 1.5 \). From the definition of numerical aperture, the sine of the limiting angle of O1 must necessarily be smaller than the air objective.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point I found it amusing that the authors cited "complexity" as a reason for why their approach is superior to adaptive optics in the introduction of this paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Questions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The authors suggest a different approach where a mirror is placed after O2 so that it also serves as O3 and use a beam splitter to direct the light leaving O2 onto a camera. Why don't light sheet microscopes use this setup? Is it because of a loss of photons due to the beam splitter?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Range of Operation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The equation for the path length difference between points in object space depends on the assumption of small object distances. This assumption places a limit on the range of validity of this approach. To quantify this limit, the authors computed the Strehl ratio of the phase of the wavefront in the pupil. Honestly, the calculations of this section look tedious. In the end, and after "some routine but rather protracted calculations, a simple result emerges." The simple result looks kind of ugly, depending, among other things on the sine to the eigth power of the aperture angle. It looks like the approach is valid for distances of several tens of microns on both sides of the focal plane of O1, which is in fact quite useful for many biological samples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ironically, the authors decide at this point that adaptive optics, the approach to remote focusing that is too complex, probably isn't that bad after all. It can be used to extend the range of validity of the authors' approach by correcting the higher order terms that are dropped in the binomial expansion for the optical path difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors go on to experimentally verify the approach in a rather unremarkable experiment of taking z-stacks of beads in two different setups. The PSF in their approach is much less aberrated than a normal widefield microscope over an axial range of about \( \pm 40 \mu m \).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall I quite like the paper because of its simplified theoretical model and clear explantion of the sine condition. I would argue, though, that the approach is not necessarily less complex than some of the alternatives that they rule out in the introduction. Admittedly, arguments over complexity are usually subjective and this doesn't necessarily mean the paper is of low quality. Given that many light sheet approaches are now based on this method, the paper serves as a good theoretical grounding into why remote focusing works and, in some cases, may be necessary.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>microscopy</category><category>optics</category><guid>https://kylemdouglass.com/posts/literature-review-an-optical-technique-for-remote-focusing-in-microscopy/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2024 11:43:39 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>